<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-claise-netmod-external-transaction-id-00">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="External Transaction ID">External Transaction ID for Configuration Changes</title>
    <author fullname="Benoit Claise" initials="B" surname="Claise">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>
      <address>
        <email>benoit.claise@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Jean Quilbeuf" initials="J" surname="Quilbeuf ">
      <organization>Huawei</organization>
      <address>
        <email>jean.quilbeuf@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author initials="J." surname="Lindblad" fullname="Jan Lindblad">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <email>jlindbla@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date/>
    <area>OPS</area>
    <workgroup>NETMOD</workgroup>
    <abstract>
      <t>
        Network equipements are often configured by a variety of network management systems (NMS), protocols and people.
        Each NMS might have its own task to perform and these taks can overlap, leading to two different NMS reverting each other modifications on the same network equipement.
        Also, the configuration pushed by an NMS can be modified by an engineer or some protocol.
        In turn, this can bring services down and desynchronize NMSs from their managed network equipement.
        We propose a mechanism to map the configuration modifications their source, up to the service request in the case of NMSs.
        Such a mechansims would facilitate the troubleshooting and post morterm analysis.
        Also, in case of more automated systems, the system could automatically identify two conflicting service request, find a solution to the conflict and close the loop by sending new instructions to the conflicting NMSs.
        This draft proposes a new YANG model to log all the configuration changes.
        In the context of NETCONF, with compatible NMS, the model would also contain a reference provided by the NMS itself, to map back to the service request. 
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Terminology" anchor="terminology">
      <t>
         The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
         NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
         "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
         described in BCP 14 <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/>
         when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
      <t>
        This draft focuses on cases where the network is configured by several NMS that use NETCONF <xref target="RFC6241"/> to update the configuration of the device.
        For instance, a network service orchestrator might receive on its northbound interface a service request to create a new service instance, following a service model <xref target="RFC8309"/> described using YANG <xref target="RFC6020"/>.  
        The orchestrator will then use NETCONF, as a client, to push the configuration needed to create the service.
        The configured network elements, which act as NETCONF servers, are likely to keep track of the modification as part of the commit history.
        However, the only information available about the configuration change is the username of the account that triggered the change. 
        In particular, the source of the modification is not available.
      </t>
      <t>
        In most cases, there isn’t a single NMS configuring all the devices.
        Usually, engineer can log in directly to devices to modify the configuration.
        Some protcols can also alter the configuration.
        Finally, there are cases where several NMSs are concurently configuring the devices.
      </t>
      <t>
        When several NMSs are used to configure the network, the same network element or NETCONF server can be configured by different NMSs or NETCONF server.
        In that case, the configuration or services configured by the first client might be impacted by the configuration pushed by the second client.
        That impact is not always easy to detect, especially if the first client is not aware of the modification done by the second client and thus is in a correct state internally.
        Troubleshooting such systems might be involved. 
        In the best case, there is a dedicated user for each client and the timestamp of the modification allows to find the reason why the second client did the modification.
        In the worst case, everything is done by the same user and some more tricks must be done to identify the source of the second modification.
      </t>
      <t>
        In order to enable automation, we need to be able to automatically detect such conflicts, analyze their cause and automatically arbitrate them at a highest level.
        While arbitration is outside of the scope of this draft, finding out why the two NMSs are in conflict and possibly finding conflicting service requests is a good use case for this draft.
        This requires mapping the changes seen on the devices to changes seen on the NMSs.
      </t>
      <t>
        In <xref target="I-D.lindblad-netconf-transaction-id"/>, the concept of a NETCONF transaction ID is proposed. 
          The goal of this draft is to speed up the re-synchronization process between a client and a server, by using a common transaction ID.         
          If the current transaction ID on the server is the same as the last one known by the client, then both are synchronized. 
          Else the client can request the diff from the latest transaction ID it knows.
          In our case, the transaction ID could be use to make the link between the changes done on the server and the need for these changes .
      </t>
      <t>
        Our proposed solution is to log every configuration modification.
        Along with the modification, we also log, when available, the information needed to retrieve both the client and the reference for that transaction sent by the client.
        If the client is a NMS, the request sent by the client might have been for the instantiation or modification of a new service.
        In the end, when such a conflict is detected, we could identify the two conflicting requests and present them to the operator or to the automation framework.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="yang-module" title="YANG Module">
      <t> We present in this section the YANG module for modelling the information about the configuration modifications. </t>
      <section anchor="module-tree" title="Overview">
        <t> The tree representation <xref target="RFC8340"/> of our YANG module is depicted in <xref target="module-tree-fig"/> </t>
        <figure anchor="module-tree-fig" title="Tree representation of ietf-external-transaction-id YANG module">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
module: ietf-external-transaction-id
  +--ro configuration-changes
     +--ro configuration-change* [local-commit-id]
        +--ro local-commit-id            string
        +--ro username                   string
        +--ro timestamp                  yang:date-and-time
        +--ro external-transaction-id?   ietf-netconf-txid:etag-t
        +--ro client-id?                 string
            ]]>
          </artwork>
        </figure>
        <t> 
          The local-commit-id represent the local id of the configuration changes.
          It can be used to retrieve the local configuration changes that happend during that transaction.
        </t>
        <t>
          The username and timestamp are mandatory and must contain the local
          username that triggered the configuration change and the date at which
          this modification occurred.
        </t>
        <t> 
          The external-transaction-id is the id for the client of the transaction that lead to the changes in local-commit-id.
          The client-id shoud identify the client that triggered the changes.
          Both fields are optional and should be filled when the client supports it.
        </t>
        <t>
          With both the client-id and the external-transaction-id, a human or a program should be able to find the source of the transaction.
          For instance, if the client is a network service orchestrator, the source of the transaction could be a service request.
        </t>
        <t>
          Q? Should we include the transition ID as a reference ? Do we target earlier adoption even in the full mechansim described in <xref target="I-D.lindblad-netconf-transaction-id"/> is not supported by the device ?
        </t>
      </section>
      
      <section anchor="module-code" title="YANG module ietf-external-transaction-id">
        <t>&lt;CODE BEGINS&gt; file "ietf-external-transaction-id@2021-11-03.yang"</t>
        <figure>
          <artwork><![CDATA[
module ietf-external-transaction-id {
  yang-version 1.1;
  namespace "urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:yang:ietf-external-transaction-id";
  prefix ext-txid;

  import ietf-yang-types {
    prefix yang;
    reference
      "RFC 6991: Common YANG Data Types";
  }
  import ietf-netconf-txid {
    prefix ietf-netconf-txid;
  }

  organization
    "IETF NETCONF (Network Configuration) Working Group";
  contact
    "WG Web:   <https://datatracker.ietf.org/wg/netconf/>
     WG List:  <mailto:netconf@ietf.org>
     Author:   Benoit Claise  <mailto:benoit.claise@huawei.com>
     Author:   Jean Quilbeuf  <mailto:jean.quilbeuf@huawei.com>;
     Author:   Jan Linblad    <mailto:jlindbla@cisco.com>";
  description
    "This module

     The key words 'MUST', 'MUST NOT', 'REQUIRED', 'SHALL',
     'SHALL NOT', 'SHOULD', 'SHOULD NOT', 'RECOMMENDED',
     'NOT RECOMMENDED', 'MAY', and 'OPTIONAL' in this document
     are to be interpreted as described in BCP 14 (RFC 2119)
     (RFC 8174) when, and only when, they appear in all
     capitals, as shown here.

     Copyright (c) 2021 IETF Trust and the persons identified as
     authors of the code.  All rights reserved.

     Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or
     without modification, is permitted pursuant to, and subject
     to the license terms contained in, the Simplified BSD License
     set forth in Section 4.c of the IETF Trust's Legal Provisions
     Relating to IETF Documents
     (https://trustee.ietf.org/license-info).
     This version of this YANG module is part of RFC XXXX; see the
     RFC itself for full legal notices.  ";

  revision 2021-11-03 {
    description
      "Initial revision";
    reference
      "RFC xxxx: Title to be completed";
  }

  container configuration-changes {
    config false;
    description
      "Container for changes in the configuration";
    list configuration-change {
      key "local-commit-id";
      description
        "List of configuration changes, identified by their
         local-commit-id";
      leaf local-commit-id {
        type string;
        description
          "Id as saved by the server. Can be used to retrieve
           the corresponding changes using the server mechanism
           if available.";
      }
      leaf username {
        type string;
        mandatory true;
        description
          "Name of the user that triggered the configuration
           change.";
      }
      leaf timestamp {
        type yang:date-and-time;
        mandatory true;
        description
          "Timestamp of the configuration change";
      }
      leaf external-transaction-id {
        type ietf-netconf-txid:etag-t;
        description
          "External transaction ID, sent by the client. Can be
           used by the client to find out the corresponding
           changes.";
      }
      leaf client-id {
        type string;
        description
          "ID of the client doing the modification, to further query
           information about the corresponding change.";
      }
    }
  }
}
    ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>&lt;CODE ENDS&gt;</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
    </section>
    <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
        This document includes no request to IANA.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Contributors">
    </section>
    <section title="Open Issues">
      <t>
        ...
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6020"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6241"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8340"?>
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8309"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8199"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.draft-lindblad-netconf-transaction-id-00"?>
    </references>
    <?rfc needLines="100"?>
    <section title="Changes between revisions">
      <t> Initial version
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
      <t>
          ...
        </t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
<!-- Local Variables: -->
<!-- fill-column:72 -->
<!-- End: -->
